<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en">
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="application/xhtml+xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Glossary</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h1>
			Glossary
		</h1>
		<dl>
			<dt>
				<a name="ascii" />
				ASCII
			</dt>
			<dd>
				American Standard Code for Information Interchange.  The predominant computer encoding for the English alphabet.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="c" />
				C
			</dt>
			<dd>
				A programming language developed in 1969 by Dennis Ritchie at AT&amp;T Bell Labs.  This is the language of
				choice for <a class="term" href="#unix">UNIX</a> development.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="command_line" />
				Command Line
			</dt>
			<dd>
				The text environment for operating <a class="term" href="#unix">UNIX</a> systems.  Often replaced by graphical
				windowing systems such as the <a class="external" href="http://www.xorg.org">X Window System</a>.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="english_spacing" />
				English Spacing
			</dt>
			<dd>
				The practise of using two spaces between sentences as punctuated by <span class="screen">.</span>, <span
					class="screen">!</span>, or <span class="screen">?</span>.  This applies even in the event that a sentence
				is quoted or parenthesised, where the spaces follow the final sentence enclosure.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="html" />
				HTML
			</dt>
			<dd>
				Hypertext markup language.  A structured mark-up language standardised by the <a class="external"
					href="http://www.w3.org">W3C</a>.  This is the predominant language for formatting world wide web
				content.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="libc" />
				libc
			</dt>
			<dd>
				The C Standard Library.  A set of functions (including <a class="term" href="#system_call">system calls</a>) in
				the <a class="term" href="#c">C programming language</a>.  Standardised by <a class="term"
					href="#posix">POSIX</a>, among other standards bodies.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="man_pages" />
				Man Pages
			</dt>
			<dd>
				Short form of <q>UNIX manual pages</q>.  System documentation for <a class="term" href="#unix">UNIX</a> systems.
				Usually viewed using the <span class="cmd">man</span> utility, which pages formatted manual documents using to
				the screen.  Man pages are formatted by a utility such as <span class="cmd">troff</span> or <span
					class="cmd">mandoc</span>.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="mdoc" />
				Mdoc
			</dt>
			<dd>
				Language for formatting <a class="term" href="#man_pages">man pages</a>.  Originally one of several available
				macro package in the <span class="lang"><a class="term" href="#roff">roff</a></span> language for the <span
					class="cmd">troff</span> text processor.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="mdoc_macro" />
				Mdoc Macro
			</dt>
			<dd>
				A short (two or three-letter) instruction in a <a class="term" href="#mdoc">mdoc</a> document.  Can accept flags
				or arguments.  These macros were traditionally implemented as blocks in the <span class="lang"><a class="term"
						href="#roff">roff</a></span> language.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="mdoc_scope" />
				Mdoc Scope
			</dt>
			<dd>
				The rules governing how <a class="term" href="#mdoc_macro">macros</a> accept arguments, which can be text or
				nested macros.  These rules depend on the macro and can be quite complex.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="posix" />
				POSIX
			</dt>
			<dd>
				Portable Operating System Interface for Unix.  Most recently released as <a class="external"
					href="http://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9699919799/">POSIX.1-2008</a>, IEEE Std 1003.1-2008.
					Informally called UNIX08.  Standards document for all UNIX implementations.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="roff" />
				Roff
			</dt>
			<dd>
				A document language written for the original <a class="term" href="#unix">UNIX</a> implementation in 1970.  This
				language was used for text processing.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="rtf" />
				RTF
			</dt>
			<dd>
				Rich text format.  Proprietary document file format used in some popular word processors.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="system_call" />
				System Call
			</dt>
			<dd>
				A machine instruction that triggers the operating system to perform a privileged operation on behalf of the
				user.  A typical example is to write a region of memory to a file.  In the <a class="term" href="#libc">C
					standard library</a>, these instructions are encoded as function calls such as <span
					class="func">write</span>.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="terminal" />
				Terminal
			</dt>
			<dd>
				The <a class="term" href="#command_line">command line</a> environment on a computer.  This can either refer to a
				terminal utility run within a graphical environment or the computer screen itself in text mode.
			</dd>
			<dt>
				<a name="unix" />
				UNIX
			</dt>
			<dd>
				Computer system originally developed by AT&amp;T Bell Labs in 1969.
				Modern open-source derivations include <a class="external" href="http://www.gnu.org">GNU/Linux</a>, <a
					class="external" href="http://www.freebsd.org">FreeBSD</a>, <a class="external"
					href="http://www.netbsd.org">NetBSD</a>, <a class="external" href="http://www.openbsd.org">OpenBSD</a>,
				etc.
			</dd>
		</dl>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="/cgi-bin/cvsweb/glossary.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
