<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Case Study</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h3 id="case_study_cmd">
			Case Study
		</h3>
		<p>
			I now introduce a case study of a real-world manual, in particular the <a href="commands.xml#cmd_echo"
				class="cmd">echo</a> utility from <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#openbsd">OpenBSD</a>.  The original file
			may be viewed on-line at <a class="external"
				href="http://www.openbsd.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb/src/bin/echo/echo.1">src/bin/echo/echo.1</a>, file version 1.20.  I
			choose this mainly because of its simplicity.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\"&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;$&#8203;OpenBSD: echo.1,v 1.20 2010/09/03 09:53:20 jmc Exp $&#8203;
			<br />
			.\"&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;$&#8203;NetBSD: echo.1,v 1.7 1995/03/21 09:04:26 cgd Exp $&#8203;
		</div>
		<p>
			These initial comments are automatically created by the source-control system <a href="commands.xml#cmd_cvs"
				class="cmd">cvs</a>, which fills in information about the last editor.  I'll talk about revision control and
			those funny dollar-sign enclosures in <a href="part3.xml">Part 3</a>.  These particular comments indicate that the file
			was initially imported from <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#netbsd">NetBSD</a> in 1995, where it was last edited by
			<span class="screen">cgd</span> (a system name, not the user's real name).  It was last edited in OpenBSD, its current
			form, by <span class="screen">jmc</span> in 2010.
		</p>
		<p>
			If you're keeping your manual under source control, it's usually a good idea to begin your file with a similar line.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\"&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;$&#8203;Id$
		</div>
		<p>
			A tab character separates the comment marker from the text.  Again, this will be covered later in this book &mdash;
			don't worry if it looks strange.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\" Copyright (c) 1990, 1993
			<br />
			.\"	The Regents of the University of California.  All rights reserved.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" This code is derived from software contributed to Berkeley by
			<br />
			.\" the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, Inc.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
			<br />
			.\" modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
			<br />
			.\" are met:
			<br />
			.\" 1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
			<br />
			.\"    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
			<br />
			.\" 2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
			<br />
			.\"    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
			<br />
			.\"    documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
			<br />
			.\" 3. Neither the name of the University nor the names of its contributors
			<br />
			.\"    may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software
			<br />
			.\"    without specific prior written permission.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE REGENTS AND CONTRIBUTORS ``AS IS'' AND
			<br />
			.\" ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
			<br />
			.\" IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
			<br />
			.\" ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE REGENTS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
			<br />
			.\" FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
			<br />
			.\" DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS
			<br />
			.\" OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
			<br />
			.\" HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT
			<br />
			.\" LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY
			<br />
			.\" OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
			<br />
			.\" SUCH DAMAGE.
		</div>
		<p>
			This long comment is the license and copyright of the source file.  Of course, our use of this source file is compatible
			with the license, as may be read from the text itself!
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\"	@(#)echo.1	8.1 (Berkeley) 7/22/93
		</div>
		<p>
			This comment is of historical note.  The <span class="screen">@(#)</span> sequence was inserted by the <a
				href="commands.xml#cmd_sccs" class="cmd">sccs</a> utility (Source Code Control System).  Although this utility
			is part of <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#posix">POSIX</a>.1-2008, it has mostly been replaced by <a
				href="commands.xml#cmd_cvs" class="cmd">cvs</a>.  You'll probably never encounter this string in your own
			manuals, so it's safe to disregard.
		</p>
		<p>
			At this point the manual content itself begins.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Dd $&#8203;Mdocdate: September 3 2010 &#8203;$
			<br />
			.Dt ECHO 1
			<br />
			.Os
		</div>
		<p>
			This indicates that the manual's title is <span class="screen">ECHO</span> in category <span class="cat">1</span>
			(utilities) for the current installed operating system.  The <span class="screen">$&#8203;Mdocdate$</span> enclosure is
			similar to that as defined at the top of the file with <span class="screen">$&#8203;OpenBSD$</span>.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh NAME
			<br />
			.Nm echo
			<br />
			.Nd write arguments to the standard output
		</div>
		<p>
			This documents a single command, the <a href="commands.xml#cmd_echo" class="cmd">echo</a> command, which does as
			mentioned.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh SYNOPSIS
			<br />
			.Nm echo
			<br />
			.Op Fl n
			<br />
			.Op Ar string ...
		</div>
		<p>
			The command accepts a single optional flag, <span class="cmdflag">n</span>, and an arbitrary number of optional
			arguments <span class="cmdarg">string</span>.  Note that re-stating the command name for the <a
				href="macros.xml#macro_nm" class="macro">Nm</a> is superfluous in this case.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh DESCRIPTION
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Nm
			<br />
			utility writes any specified operands, separated by single blank
			<br />
			.Pq Sq \ \&amp;
			<br />
			characters and followed by a newline
			<br />
			.Pq Sq \en
			<br />
			character, to the standard
			<br />
			output.
			<br />
			When no operands are given, only the newline is written.
		</div>
		<p>
			The <span class="sec">DESCRIPTION</span> opens with a brief explanation of the utility and its output.  The strange set
			of backslash-escaped characters <span class="screen">\ \&amp;</span> is required to make the doubly-nested macros <a
				href="macros.xml#macro_pq" class="macro">Pq</a> and <a href="macros.xml#macro_sq" class="macro">Sq</a>
			(parenthesise and single-quote, respectively) correctly enclose a single space.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Pp
			<br />
			The options are as follows:
			<br />
			.Bl -tag -width Ds
			<br />
			.It Fl n
			<br />
			Do not print the trailing newline character.
			<br />
			.El
		</div>
		<p>
			This follows the standard form of documenting flags and arguments as a term/definition list.  Each one &mdash; in this
			case only one &mdash; is documented in alphabetical ordered.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh EXIT STATUS
			<br />
			.Ex -std echo
		</div>
		<p>
			Notes the standard exit sequence.  Note that the argument to <a href="macros.xml#macro_ex" class="macro">Ex</a> is
			superfluous, as only one command is listed for the manual.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh SEE ALSO
			<br />
			.Xr csh 1 ,
			<br />
			.Xr ksh 1 ,
			<br />
			.Xr printf 1
		</div>
		<p>
			Although these weren't cited in other sections of the manual, the author felt it necessary to link to them.  This is
			probably because both <span class="screen">csh</span> and <span class="screen">ksh</span> include internal
			implementations of a function by the same name.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh STANDARDS
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Nm
			<br />
			utility is compliant with the
			<br />
			.St -p1003.1-2008
			<br />
			specification.
			<br />
			.Pp
			<br />
			The flag
			<br />
			.Op Fl n
			<br />
			is an extension to that specification.
			<br />
			.Pp
			<br />
			.Nm
			<br />
			also exists as a built-in to
			<br />
			.Xr csh 1
			<br />
			and
			<br />
			.Xr ksh 1 ,
			<br />
			though with a different syntax.
		</div>
		<p>
			This last section fully describes the utility's conformance to the <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#posix">POSIX</a>
			standard, which is very important to those writing portable utilities.  The <a href="macros.xml#macro_st"
				class="macro">St</a> macro expands into the relevant standard's full name.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part1-2.xml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/part1-1-3.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
