<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en">
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="application/xhtml+xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Layout</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h2>
			Layout
		</h2>
		<p>
			An <span class="lang">mdoc</span> document body is divided into sections.  The names and ordering of these sections is
			dictated by convention extending to the first published edition of UNIX.  The original forms of these sections are
			documented in the <a class="external" href="http://www.cs.bell-labs.com/who/dmr/1stEdman.html">UNIX Programmer's
				Manual</a>, First Edition, 1971:
		</p>
		<blockquote cite="http://www.cs.bell-labs.com/who/dmr/1stEdman.html">
			<ul>
				<li>
					The <span class="under">name</span> section repeats the entry name and gives a very short description of its purpose.
				</li>
				<li>
					The <span class="under">synopsis</span> summarizes the use of the program being described. A few conventions are used, particularly
					in the Commands section.  Underlined words are considered literals, and are typed just as they appear.
					Square brackets ([]) around an argument indicate that the argument is optional. When an argument is
					given as name, it always refers to a file name.  Ellipses ... are used to show that the previous
					argument-prototype may be repeated.  A final convention is used by the commands themselves. An argument
					beginning with a minus sign - is often taken to mean some sort of flag argument even if it appears in a
					position where a file name could appear. Therefore, it is unwise to have files whose names begin with -.
					The description section discusses in detail the subject at hand.
				</li>
				<li>
					The <span class="under">files</span> section gives the names of files which are built into the program.
				</li>
				<li> 
					A <span class="under">see also</span> section gives pointers to related information.
				</li>
				<li>
					A <span class="under">diagnostics</span> section discusses the diagnostics that may be produced. This section tends to be as
					terse as the diagnostics themselves.
				</li>
				<li>
					The <span class="under">bugs</span> section gives known bugs and sometimes deficiencies. occasionally also the suggested fix
					is described.
				</li>
				<li>
					The <span class="under">owner</span> section gives the name of the person or persons to be consulted in case of difficulty.
					The rule has been that the last one to modify something owns it, so the owner is not necessarily the
					author.
				</li>
			</ul>
		</blockquote>
		<p>
			These conventional sections haven't changed much over the years, although more sections have been added and several have
			changed with evolving UNIX operating system conventions.  The full set of modern sections, and their order, is as
			follows.
		</p>
		<dl>
			<dt><span class="sec">NAME</span></dt>
			<dd>Name of all documented components and a collective description.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">SYNOPSIS</span></dt>
			<dd>Calling syntax of the components.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">DESCRIPTION</span></dt>
			<dd>Description of all components.  This constitutes the bulk of the manual.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">IMPLEMENTATION NOTES</span></dt>
			<dd>Specific notes on the implementation of a generic (e.g., standardised) component.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">RETURN VALUES</span></dt>
			<dd>Return values, if the components are functions.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">ENVIRONMENT</span></dt>
			<dd>Environmental variables affecting the components' operation.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">FILES</span></dt>
			<dd>Files affecting the components' operation.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">EXIT STATUS</span></dt>
			<dd>Exit status, if the components are commands.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">EXAMPLES</span></dt>
			<dd>Brief examples of invocation.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">DIAGNOSIS</span></dt>
			<dd>Error conditions, if a command or device driver.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">ERRORS</span></dt>
			<dd>Error conditions, if a function or library.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">SEE ALSO</span></dt>
			<dd>Links to other relevant manuals or references.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">STANDARDS</span></dt>
			<dd>Implemented or referenced standards.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">HISTORY</span></dt>
			<dd>A brief history of the components.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">AUTHORS</span></dt>
			<dd>The authors of the components.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">CAVEATS</span></dt>
			<dd>Caveats regarding the components' operation.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">BUGS</span></dt>
			<dd>Known bugs in the components.</dd>
			<dt><span class="sec">SECURITY CONSIDERATIONS</span></dt>
			<dd>Security precautions beyond the scope of the components.</dd>
		</dl>
		<p>
			Only the <span class="sec">NAME</span> and <span class="sec">DESCRIPTION</span> sections are required in the document
			body, although a <span class="sec">SYNOPSIS</span> should appear for most manuals as well.  Other sections are commonly
			found depending on the category.  For example, <span class="sec">RETURN VALUES</span> is found for most category <span
				class="cat">3</span> and <span class="cat">2</span> manuals; while <span class="sec">EXIT STATUS</span> is found
			for most category <span class="cat">1</span>, <span class="cat">6</span>, and <span class="cat">8</span> manuals.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part2-3-1.xhtml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/part2-3.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
