<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Quotation</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h3 id="quotation">
			Quotation
		</h3>
		<p>
			Several times I've mentioned how to interpret macro arguments as text &mdash; instead of, say, other macros &mdash; by
			quotation.  In this section, I formalise the notion of quoting arguments.  The issue of quotation is fairly complex
			owing to <span class="lang">mdoc</span>'s predecessor, <a class="term lang" href="glossary.xml#roff">roff</a>.  
		</p>
		<p>
			In short, quoting arguments to macros passes the enclosed text verbatim as a single argument.  An obvious case follows:
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Fl "Ar"
		</div>
		<p>
			By quoting <span class="screen">Ar</span>, it is passed verbatim to <a class="macro" href="macros.xml#macro_fl">Fl</a>
			If not, it would be interpreted as the macro <a class="macro" href="macros.xml#macro_ar">Ar</a> and open a new macro
			scope.  What's worse is that the syntax is entirely legal!  This illustrates a minor short-coming of <span
				class="lang">mdoc</span>: beginners may unwittingly invoke macros (such as <a class="macro"
				href="macros.xml#macro_ar">Ar</a> in our example).  Printing a warning would cause more harm than good with
			well-formed manuals; thus, it's the responsibility of the document author to double-check that macro instructions are
			properly treated. 
		</p>
		<p>
			This condition could have been avoided by beginning the argument <span class="screen">Ar</span> with a zero-width
			escape, such as <span class="screen">\&amp;Ar</span>.  The need for quotation is more obvious with the <a class="macro"
				href="macros.xml#macro_fn">Fn</a> macro:
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Fn 
			<span style="border: 1px dashed green;">int</span> 
			<span style="border: 1px dashed green;">foo</span> 
			<span style="border: 1px dashed green;">int</span>
			<span style="border: 1px dashed green;">bar</span>
		</div>
		<p>
			The syntax of <a class="macro" href="macros.xml#macro_fn">Fn</a> is that it first accepts an optional function type,
			then a function name, then arguments to the function.  These arguments usually include a type followed by a name.  In
			our example, <span class="screen">int</span> refers to the function type, <span class="screen">foo</span> to the name,
			and both <span class="screen">int</span> and <span class="screen">bar</span> as separate arguments.
		</p>
		<p>
			Our intention, however, was to have <span class="screen">int bar</span> considered a single argument.  To do so, we
			would need to quote.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Fn 
			<span style="border: 1px dashed green;">int</span> 
			<span style="border: 1px dashed green;">foo</span> 
			"<span style="border: 1px dashed green;">int bar</span>"
		</div>
		<p>
			The <span class="screen">int bar</span> argument is now passed intact to the macro.
		</p>
		<p>
			To include quotation marks in quoted text, use two quotation marks in a row.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Li <span style="border: 1px dashed green;">"""&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;"</span>
		</div>
		<p>
			This artificial invocation passes a quotation mark followed by four whitespaces to the <a href="macros.xml#macro_li"
				class="macro">Li</a> macro.  It is, however, unwise to use this language component: it's jarring to those
			expecting symmetric quotes, and easy to mis-type, leaving runaway quotes.  It's safer to use an escape, such as <span
				class="screen">\(dq</span>, instead of pair-wise quotations.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-contents"><a href="toc.xml">Contents</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part2-2.xml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/part2-1-6.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
