<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en">
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="application/xhtml+xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Case Study</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h3>
			Case Study
		</h3>
		<p>
			I now introduce a case study of a real-world function library manual, in particular the manual for the <span
				class="func">getc</span>, <span class="func">fgetc</span>, <span class="func">getw</span>, and <span
				class="func">getchar</span> functions from <a class="external" href="http://www.openbsd.org">OpenBSD</a>.  The
			original file may be viewed on-line at <a class="external"
				href="http://www.openbsd.orghttp://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/src/lib/libc/stdio/getc.3">src/lib/libc/stdio/getc.3</a>.  This is
			not the manual for the full function library, but only a handful of similar functions.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\"	$&#8203;OpenBSD: getc.3,v 1.12 2007/05/31 19:19:31 jmc Exp &#8203;$
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" Copyright (c) 1990, 1991, 1993
			<br />
			.\"	The Regents of the University of California.  All rights reserved.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" This code is derived from software contributed to Berkeley by
			<br />
			.\" Chris Torek and the American National Standards Committee X3,
			<br />
			.\" on Information Processing Systems.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
			<br />
			.\" modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
			<br />
			.\" are met:
			<br />
			.\" 1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
			<br />
			.\"    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
			<br />
			.\" 2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
			<br />
			.\"    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
			<br />
			.\"    documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
			<br />
			.\" 3. Neither the name of the University nor the names of its contributors
			<br />
			.\"    may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software
			<br />
			.\"    without specific prior written permission.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE REGENTS AND CONTRIBUTORS ``AS IS'' AND
			<br />
			.\" ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
			<br />
			.\" IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
			<br />
			.\" ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE REGENTS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
			<br />
			.\" FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
			<br />
			.\" DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS
			<br />
			.\" OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
			<br />
			.\" HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT
			<br />
			.\" LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY
			<br />
			.\" OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
			<br />
			.\" SUCH DAMAGE.
		</div>
		<p>
			The <span class="cmd">cvs</span> identifier, copyright, and license comments of this file are very similar to that of
			the <a href="part1-1-3.xhtml#case_study_cmd">Case Study</a> for commands.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Dd $&#8203;Mdocdate: May 31 2007 &#8203;$
			<br />
			.Dt GETC 3
			<br />
			.Os
		</div>
		<p>
			This classifies our manual in category <span class="cat">3</span> as a function or function library.  The title of the
			manual, <span class="screen">GETC</span>, is chosen as the most general of those functions listed below in the <span
				class="sec">NAME</span> section.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh NAME
			<br />
			.Nm fgetc ,
			<br />
			.Nm getc ,
			<br />
			.Nm getchar ,
			<br />
			.Nm getw
			<br />
			.Nd get next character or word from input stream
		</div>
		<p>
			Lists (alphabetically) all the functions that will be documented, and some general notes about their collective
			function.  We next jump down into the <span class="sec">SYNOPSIS</span>; since this set of functions is part of the <a
				class="term" href="glossary.xhtml#libc">C Standard Library</a>, it needs no special linking information.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh SYNOPSIS
			<br />
			.Fd #include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
			<br />
			.Ft int
			<br />
			.Fn fgetc "FILE *stream"
			<br />
			.Ft int
			<br />
			.Fn getc "FILE *stream"
			<br />
			.Ft int
			<br />
			.Fn getchar "void"
			<br />
			.Ft int
			<br />
			.Fn getw "FILE *stream"
		</div>
		<p>
			This documents the calling syntax of all functions.  Note that the <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_fd" class="macro">Fd</a>
			macro is used instead of the <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_in" class="macro">In</a> macro.  This invocation is
			historically relevant, but new manuals should always use <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_in" class="macro">In</a>.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.In stdio.h
		</div>
		<p>
			Next, each function and its arguments is explained as a free-flowing paragraph.  This was probably chosen instead of
			using a list item for each argument (with <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_bl" class="macro">Bl</a>) due to the small number
			of arguments.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh DESCRIPTION
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Fn fgetc
			<br />
			function obtains the next input character (if present) from the stream
			<br />
			pointed at by
			<br />
			.Fa stream ,
			<br />
			or the next character pushed back on the stream via
			<br />
			.Xr ungetc 3 .
			<br />
			.Pp
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Fn getc
			<br />
			function acts essentially identically to
			<br />
			.Fn fgetc ,
			<br />
			but is a macro that expands in-line.
			<br />
			.Pp
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Fn getchar
			<br />
			function is equivalent to
			<br />
			.Fn getc
			<br />
			with the argument
			<br />
			.Em stdin .
			<br />
			.Pp
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Fn getw
			<br />
			function obtains the next
			<br />
			.Li int
			<br />
			(if present)
			<br />
			from the stream pointed at by
			<br />
			.Fa stream .
		</div>
		<p>
			The usage of the <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_em" class="macro">Em</a> macro is not correct: the <a
				href="macros.xhtml#macro_va" class="macro">Va</a> or <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_dv" class="macro">Dv</a> macro
			would have been more appropriate.  The same applies to the <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_li" class="macro">Li</a>.  The
			<span class="lang">mdoc</span> language is semantic, so using presentation macros such as <a
				href="macros.xhtml#macro_li" class="macro">Li</a> and <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_em" class="macro">Em</a> is
			discouraged.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh RETURN VALUES
			<br />
			If successful, these routines return the next requested object from the
			<br />
			.Fa stream .
			<br />
			If the stream is at end-of-file or a read error occurs, the routines return
			<br />
			.Dv EOF .
			<br />
			The routines
			<br />
			.Xr feof 3
			and
			<br />
			.Xr ferror 3
			<br />
			must be used to distinguish between end-of-file and error.
			<br />
			If an error occurs, the global variable
			<br />
			.Va errno
			<br />
			is set to indicate the error.
			<br />
			The end-of-file condition is remembered, even on a terminal, and all
			<br />
			subsequent attempts to read will return
			<br />
			.Dv EOF
			<br />
			until the condition is cleared with
			<br />
			.Xr clearerr 3 .
			<br />
			.Sh SEE ALSO
			<br />
			.Xr ferror 3 ,
			<br />
			.Xr fopen 3 ,
			<br />
			.Xr fread 3 ,
			<br />
			.Xr putc 3 ,
			<br />
			.Xr ungetc 3
		</div>
		<p>
			All possible return values are correctly documented in the <span class="sec">RETURN VALUES</span> section and relevant
			functions cross-linked in the <span class="sec">SEE ALSO</span> section.  Note that the cross-linked manuals are also
			alphabetically sorted.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh STANDARDS
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Fn fgetc ,
			<br />
			.Fn getc ,
			<br />
			and
			<br />
			.Fn getchar
			<br />
			functions conform to
			<br />
			.St -ansiC .
		</div>
		<p>
			Noting standards conformance is extremely important: it allows programmers and administrators to depend on your
			component in a cross-platform fashion.  These functions are part of the <a class="term" href="glossary.xhtml#libc">C
				Standard Library</a>.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh BUGS
			<br />
			Since
			<br />
			.Dv EOF
			<br />
			is a valid integer value,
			<br />
			.Xr feof 3
			<br />
			and
			<br />
			.Xr ferror 3
			<br />
			must be used to check for failure after calling
			<br />
			.Fn getw .
			<br />
			.Pp
			<br />
			Since the size and byte order of an
			<br />
			.Vt int
			<br />
			may vary from one machine to another,
			<br />
			.Fn getw
			<br />
			is not recommended for portable applications.
		</div>
		<p>
			The <span class="sec">BUGS</span> section should be used very carefully &mdash; bugs preferrably should be fixed.  In
			this section, design bugs have been documented.  Whether the <span class="sec">CAVEATS</span> section would be more
			appropriate is up to the manual author.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part1-4.xhtml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/part1-2-3.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
