<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en">
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="application/xhtml+xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Part 1, Chapter 1: Commands</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h2>
			Commands
		</h2>
		<p>
			Commands are the way in which a user operates her computer.  Already I've noted the <span class="cmd">man</span>
			command: if you've interacted with a UNIX machine, you've probably run at least <code class="cmdline">man intro</code>
			or <code class="cmdline">man man</code> to learn about your system.
		</p>
		<p>
			In this chapter, I'll discuss how to document these commands with <span class="lang">mdoc</span>.  
		</p>
		<p>
			This may be unfamiliar if you're accustomed to graphical interfaces&mdash;all of our examples will refer to
			command-line, text-based commands.  If your target environment isn't a UNIX system, it's a good idea to read these
			examples anyway, as as they will expose the rudimentary structure of the <span class="lang">mdoc</span> language.  As
			mentioned before, reading an introductory text on UNIX will help avoid confusion.
		</p>
		<p>
			Let's begin by making a mental checklist for the criteria that make a good manual for a command.
		</p>
		<p>
			This checklist arises by inverting what a manual reader expects in opening a manual.  Namely: what does the command do
			and how do I operate it?
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Do I describe the calling syntax of the command?</li>
			<li>Do I describe each flag and argument of the command?</li>
			<li>Do I describe the command's operation?</li>
			<li>Do I describe the command's exit status?</li>
			<li>Do I describe referenced files and environment variables?</li>
		</ul>
		<p>
			Above all, the best litmus test is whether a colleague or friend can read your manual and be able to use your command
			without any assistance on your part.  Don't be discouraged by how this can take several tries to get right!
		</p>
		<p>
			I'll begin with a simple command, <span class="cmd">hi</span>, which prints <span class="screen">hello, world</span> to
			the screen.  I'll then add some command-line arguments to this command.  By the time you exit this chapter, you should
			have a grasp of <span class="lang">mdoc</span> syntax and some of its more widely-used macros.
		</p>
		<p>
			In general, I'll refer to commands as <span class="cmd">command</span> <span class="cmdopt"><span
					class="cmdflag">flag</span> <span class="cmdarg">farg</span></span> <span class="cmdarg">arg</span>.
		</p>
		<p>
			Here, <span class="cmd">command</span> refers to the command invocation name, <span class="cmdflag">flag</span> is a
			flag (or switch) to that command, <span class="cmdarg">farg</span> is an argument to a flag (not all flags have
			arguments), and <span class="cmdarg">arg</span> is an argument to the command.
		</p>
		<p>
			The dash in front of <span class="cmdflag">flag</span> indicates a flag, while the square brackets around 
			<span class="cmdopt"><span class="cmdflag">flag</span> <span class="cmdarg">farg</span></span> indicate an optional part of the invocation.
			Since <span class="cmdarg">arg</span> is not bracketed, it is a mandatory part of the invocation.
		</p>
		<p class="nav">
			<a href="part1-1-1.xhtml">Next</a>
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
