<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en">
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="application/xhtml+xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Case Study</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h3>
			Case Study
		</h3>
		<p>
			I now introduce a case study of a real-world system call manual, in particular the manual for the <span
				class="func">fsync</span> function from <a class="term" href="glossary.xhtml#openbsd">OpenBSD</a>.  The
			original file may be viewed on-line at <a class="external"
				href="http://www.openbsd.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb/src/lib/libc/sys/fsync.2">src/lib/libc/sys/fsync.2</a>, file version
			1.9.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\"	$&#8203;OpenBSD: fsync.2,v 1.9 2011/04/29 07:12:44 jmc Exp $
			<br />
			.\"	$&#8203;NetBSD: fsync.2,v 1.4 1995/02/27 12:32:38 cgd Exp $
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" Copyright (c) 1983, 1993
			<br />
			.\"	The Regents of the University of California.  All rights reserved.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
			<br />
			.\" modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
			<br />
			.\" are met:
			<br />
			.\" 1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
			<br />
			.\"    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
			<br />
			.\" 2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
			<br />
			.\"    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
			<br />
			.\"    documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
			<br />
			.\" 3. Neither the name of the University nor the names of its contributors
			<br />
			.\"    may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software
			<br />
			.\"    without specific prior written permission.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE REGENTS AND CONTRIBUTORS ``AS IS'' AND
			<br />
			.\" ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
			<br />
			.\" IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
			<br />
			.\" ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE REGENTS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
			<br />
			.\" FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
			<br />
			.\" DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS
			<br />
			.\" OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
			<br />
			.\" HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT
			<br />
			.\" LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY
			<br />
			.\" OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
			<br />
			.\" SUCH DAMAGE.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\"     @(#)fsync.2	8.1 (Berkeley) 6/4/93
		</div>
		<p>
			The <span class="cmd">cvs</span> identifiers (both from the current system, <a class="term"
				href="glossary.xhtml#openbsd">OpenBSD</a>, and the import source system, <a class="term"
				href="glossary.xhtml#netbsd">NetBSD</a>), copyright, license, and <span class="cmd">sccs</span> identifier (from
			the original system) are presented in the usual way.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Dd $&#8203;Mdocdate: April 29 2011 $
			<br />
			.Dt FSYNC 2
			<br />
			.Os
		</div>
		<p>
			The manual's last-modified date is maintained with the automatically-updated <span
				class="screen">$&#8203;Mdocdate$</span> sequence.  Its title is set to the single function's capitalised form,
			category <span class="cat">2</span> for system calls under the current operating system.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh NAME
			<br />
			.Nm fsync
			<br />
			.Nd "synchronize a file's in-core state with that on disk"
		</div>
		<p>
			The <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_nd" class="macro">Nd</a> macro's arguments are supefluously quoted again.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh SYNOPSIS
			<br />
			.Fd #include &lt;unistd.h&gt;
			<br />
			.Ft int
			<br />
			.Fn fsync "int fd"
		</div>
		<p>
			Again, in historical manuals, <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_fd" class="macro">Fd</a> is sometimes used instead of the
			modern <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_in" class="macro">In</a> macro.  Note also the inclusion of the function argument's
			name, <span class="screen">fd</span>, where regular C prototypes would usually only include the type.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh DESCRIPTION
			<br />
			.Fn fsync
			<br />
			causes all modified data and attributes of
			<br />
			.Fa fd
			<br />
			to be moved to a permanent storage device.
			<br />
			This normally results in all in-core modified copies
			<br />
			of buffers for the associated file to be written to a disk.
			<br />
			.Pp
			<br />
			.Fn fsync
			<br />
			should be used by programs that require a file to be in a known state,
			<br />
			for example, in building a simple transaction facility.
		</div>
		<p>
			Since <span class="func">fsync</span> is a simple function, its description is fairly straightforward.  The single
			function argument <span class="screen">fd</span> is fully described as well.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			<br />
			.Sh RETURN VALUES
			<br />
			A 0 value is returned on success.
			<br />
			A \-1 value indicates an error.
		</div>
		<p>
			This is not correct, as it omits information on the <span class="var">errno</span> global error being set.  The <a
				href="macros.xhtml#macro_rv" class="macro">Rv</a> macro should be used instead.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh ERRORS
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Fn fsync
			<br />
			fails if:
			<br />
			.Bl -tag -width Er
			<br />
			.It Bq Er EBADF
			<br />
			.Fa fd
			<br />
			is not a valid descriptor.
			<br />
			.It Bq Er EINVAL
			<br />
			.Fa fd
			<br />
			refers to a socket, not to a file.
			<br />
			.It Bq Er EIO
			<br />
			An I/O error occurred while reading from or writing to the file system.
			<br />
			.El
		</div>
		<p>
			Most (if not all) system calls set the <span class="var">errno</span> global error upon failure.  This, erroneously, was
			not mentioned in the <span class="sec">RETURN VALUES</span> section, but is documented here.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Sh SEE ALSO
			<br />
			.Xr sync 2 ,
			<br />
			.Xr sync 8
			<br />
			.Sh HISTORY
			<br />
			The
			<br />
			.Fn fsync
			<br />
			function call appeared in
			<br />
			.Bx 4.2 .
		</div>
		<p>
			Note that the cross-references in <span class="sec">SEE ALSO</span> are ordered first by section, then alphabetically.
			The <a href="macros.xhtml#macro_bx" class="macro">Bx</a> is referenced as the origin of the system call.  The <span
				class="sec">STANDARDS</span> section is sorely missing, as <span class="func">fsync</span> is a function
			specified by <a href="glossary.xhtml#posix" class="term">POSIX</a>.1-2008 standard.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part2.xhtml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/part1-4-1.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
