<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Revision Control</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h3>
			Revision Control
		</h3>
		<p>
			Several examples in this book have covered the topic of integrating <span class="lang">mdoc</span> documents into
			revision control systems.  In this section, I cover the few steps required to integrate these documents with <a
				class="cmd term" href="glossary.xml#cvs">cvs</a>.
		</p>
		<p>
			Assume a file <span class="file">foo.in.1.</span> consists of our <span class="lang">mdoc</span> source.  I assume, for
			simplicity, that it is licensed with the <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#isc_license">ISC license</a> and
			copyright-protected, both of which lead the document as a series of comments.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\" Copyright (c) 2011 Kristaps Dzonsons &lt;kristaps@bsd.lv&gt;
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this software for any
			<br />
			.\" purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
			<br />
			.\" copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
			<br />
			.\" WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
			<br />
			.\" MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
			<br />
			.\" ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
			<br />
			.\" WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
			<br />
			.\" ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
			<br />
			.\" OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.Dd August 18 2011
			<br />
			.Dt FOO 1
			<br />
			.Os
		</div>
		<p>
			The first step is to add a useful message to the top of the file as the version of the file.  This is standard practise
			in revision controlled files.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.\"&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;$&#8203;Id$
			<br />
			.\"
			<br />
			.\" Copyright (c) 2011 Kristaps Dzonsons &lt;kristaps@bsd.lv&gt;
		</div>
		<p>
			Make sure that the first line has a tab character between the <span class="screen">$&#8203;Id$</span> and leading comment
			marker.  This sequence is filled in with the file's last editor, revision, and checkin date.
		</p>
		<p>
			Some <span class="cmd">cvs</span> servers (e.g., those in <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#netbsd">NetBSD</a> and <a
				class="term" href="glossary.xml#openbsd">OpenBSD</a>) support the <span class="screen">Mdocdate</span>
			sequence.  This is filled by in <span class="cmd">cvs</span> with the check-in date.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocin">
			.Dd $&#8203;Mdocdate$
			<br />
			.Dt FOO 1
			<br />
			.Os
		</div>
		<p>
			In performing these two steps, the file's last-modified date and source identifier will be properly filled in by the
			<span class="cmd">cvs</span> server.  If your server does not support <span class="screen">Mdocdate</span>, you will
			have to maintain the date by hand, or possibly override the build rule for your file.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part3-3.xml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/part3-2-2.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
