<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Editing</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h3>
			Editing
		</h3>
		<p>
			Since <span class="lang">mdoc</span> is an ASCII-clean text format, it may be edited in any text editor.  In this
			section, I introduce a variety of editors available on most <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#unix">UNIX</a> systems.
			Since this topic is exhaustively covered in most any introductory UNIX book, I only introduce portable editors.
		</p>
		<h4>
			Ed
		</h4>
		<p>
			The <span class="cmd">ed</span> utility is a line editor standardised by <a class="term"
				href="glossary.xml#posix">POSIX</a>.1-2008.  The concept of a line editor may be familiar to those who have used
			a typewriter or teleprinter, where only the current line of input may be edited (or viewed, in some cases) at a time.
		</p>
		<p>
			Its inclusion is largely for historical reasons, as using <span class="cmd">ed</span> can be a frustrating experience
			for those accustomed to visual editors.  I don't recommend using this utility for <span class="lang">mdoc</span>,
			although its function as a line editor makes it perfect for the task.
		</p>
		<h4>
			Ex, Vi
		</h4>
		<p>
			The <span class="cmd">vi</span> and <span class="cmd">ex</span> editors were powerful additions to the UNIX system: they
			allowed visual editing of files (versus line editing as with <span class="cmd">ed</span>).  This editor has inspired a
			raft of clones, but being standardised, some form of the utility is available on all UNIX systems.  Furthermore, the
			<span class="cmd">vim</span> clone of <span class="cmd">vi</span> comes bundled with <span class="lang">mdoc</span>
			syntax highlighting.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part3-3-2.xml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/part3-3-1.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
