<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
	<head>
		<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/xml; charset=utf-8"/>
		<title>Preface</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="css/book.css" type="text/css"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<h1>
			Preface
		</h1>
		<blockquote>
			<p>
				A utility without a manual is of no utility at all.
			</p>
		</blockquote>
		<p>
			This is a guide for writing UNIX manuals in the <span class="lang"><a class="term"
					href="glossary.xml#mdoc">mdoc</a></span> language.  If you're new to writing UNIX manuals, or you want
			to learn about best practices for high-quality manuals, this book may benefit your work.
		</p>
		<p>
			To those unfamiliar with <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#unix">UNIX</a>, <span class="lang">mdoc</span> is a
			language for documenting utilities, programming functions, file and wire formats, hardware device interfaces, and so on.
			By a language I mean a structured, machine-readable document format such as <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#html">
				HTML</a>, the primary language of web pages; or <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#rtf">RTF</a>, used by word
			processors.  <span class="cmd">man</span> is the utility for querying documents in <span class="lang">mdoc</span> and
			other languages, collectively called <a class="term" href="glossary.xml#man_pages">man pages</a>.  
		</p>
		<p>
			The following, for example, is a fragment of <span class="cmd">man</span> output for the <span class="cmd">cat</span>
			command.
		</p>
		<div class="mdocout">
			<div class="mdoc-section">
				<h1>NAME</h1>
				<b class="mdoc-name">cat</b> &#8212; <span class="mdoc-desc">concatenate and print files</span></div>
			<div class="mdoc-section">
				<h1>SYNOPSIS</h1>
				<table class="mdoc-synopsis">
					<col style="width: 3.00ex;"/>
					<col/>
					<tbody>
						<tr>
							<td>
								cat
							</td>
							<td>
								&#91;<span class="mdoc-opt"><b class="mdoc-flag">&#45;benstuv</b></span>&#93; 
								&#91;<span class="mdoc-opt"><i class="mdoc-arg">file ...</i></span>&#93;
							</td>
						</tr>
					</tbody>
				</table>
			</div>
			<div class="mdoc-section">
				<h1>DESCRIPTION</h1>
				The <b class="mdoc-name">cat</b> utility reads files sequentially, writing them to the standard output. The <i
					class="mdoc-arg">file</i> operands are processed in command-line order.  If <i class="mdoc-arg">file</i>
				is a single dash (&#8216;&#8203;-&#39;) or absent, <b class="mdoc-name">cat</b> reads from
				the standard input.
			</div>
		</div>
		<p>
			Any modern UNIX system can format <span class="lang">mdoc</span> manuals without needing special software.
		</p>
		<p>
			I've mentioned UNIX several times already, but in fact, <span class="lang">mdoc</span> isn't exclusively tied to UNIX.
			Although UNIX and <span class="lang">mdoc</span> are historically linked, open source <span class="lang">mdoc</span>
			tools exist for any operating system.  Furthermore, the documentation capabilities of <span class="lang">mdoc</span>
			apply to computing systems in general &mdash; not just UNIX.
		</p>
		<p>
			In this book I'll assume you are casually familiar with <span class="cmd">man</span> and its output.  This will allow us
			to focus on manuals with the same formatted output in mind.  Thus, if you're unfamiliar with UNIX or <span
				class="cmd">man</span>, this is a good time to read an introductory text on the subject, or at the very least,
			read the output of <span class="cmdline">man man</span> (the manual page of the <span class="cmd">man</span> command).
		</p>
		<p>
			This is not a canonical reference! The <span class="lang">mdoc</span> language is not standardised.  For official
			reference, consult the manual distributed with your target computer system.  This work primarily addresses the elements
			of <span class="lang">mdoc</span> common to any UNIX deployment, noting common pitfalls in portability.
		</p>
		<table class="nav">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td class="nav-home"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/index.html">Home</a></td>
					<td class="nav-next"><a href="part1.xml">Next</a></td>
					<td class="nav-history"><a href="http://manpages.bsd.lv/cgi-bin/cvsweb/preface.xml?cvsroot=manpages">History</a></td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>
		<p class="edits">
			Last edited by $Author$ on $Date$.  Copyright &copy; 2011, Kristaps Dzonsons.  CC BY-SA.
		</p>
	</body>
</html>
